בוקר טוב *Boker tov*. All right today's דף *daf* is ס"ה *Samech
Hey* 65, we pick up at the very bottom of ס"ד עמוד
ב' *Samech Dalet Amud Bet*. We're in the middle of a debate
between רב Rav *Rav* and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* about
when you bring a new pair of goats and do the lottery
because one of the original ones died, what which goat do you
use of
the of the... let's do this again. Let's say for example the
one לעזאזל L'Azazel *L'Azazel* dies and the one לה' *L'Hashem* is still
around and you do a new lottery. So clearly in the new
lottery the one that was לעזאזל L'Azazel *L'Azazel* replaces the dead one.
But which is the one that you use לה' *L'Hashem*? Do you
use the one of the original pair or do you use the
one of the new pair? And this is a debate between רב
Rav *Rav* and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, *Rabbi Yochanan*.
רב Rav *Rav* says use the one in the original pair which
was it sounds like in the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*, the גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* says דיקא מתניתין כוותיה דרב *Dika matnisin kivasei d'Rav*. It sounds
like you take the new one of the lottery and you have
it fill in and you use the one from the original pair
as you were planning on using it. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, *Rabbi
Yochanan* and the reason the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says is because מצוה
בראשון mitzvah b'rishon, *Mitzvah barishon*, as long as that was the first
one you stick with that, whereas רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, *Rabbi Yochanan*
says no you use the one from the second pair, the one
from the first pair gets rejected, דיחוי *Dichuy*. Since there was a
period where you couldn't use the one from the first pair before
you did the new lottery, that became for a period of time
unusable, נדחה nidcha. *Nidcheh*, pushed away, and therefore it remains unusable and
you can only use the one from the second pair. So that
is the debate if it's a general question of whether we say
בעלי חיים Baalei chayim *Ba'alei chayim* is נדחים *nidchim*, can someone an
animal that's still alive and be pushed away? People might agree that
once it's dead and it becomes unusable that stigma that identity remains,
but if it's a live animal the live one לה' *L'Hashem* that's
still around does that become fully stigmatized and rejected or can it
become reusable? By the way I like that idea that as long
as something is alive that sense of dynamic it's not fully an
object it can't fully be categorized it's something that you know that
it doesn't necessarily stick with a label you add on you put
onto it I think is a very powerful idea especially in the
context of יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*, you know that sense
that we can't just be labeled and be done with.
Yeah I wouldn't exactly say that but okay.
Anyway that's a general issue about whether you say בעלי חיים Baalei
chayim, *Ba'alei chayim* is נדחים *nidchim* and that's why רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan, *Rabbi Yochanan* would say because he believes it is pushed away
you can only use the second one. רב Rav, *Rav* says no
it's not true you can use the first one and you probably
you should use you must use the first one because of מצוה
בראשון Mitzvah B'Rishon, *Mitzvah barishon*. Before we continue I don't think you
covered this yesterday and I just want to mention it because I
found it a very powerful תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*. Do you remember רב
Rav, *Rav*'s idea of מצוה בראשון Mitzvah B'Rishon, *Mitzvah barishon* is based
on a teaching of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi, *Rabbi Yossi* that says
in a similar case where you had קרבן korban פסח *Korban Pesach*
and one got lost and you had another one and you found
the original one מצוה Mitzvah בראשון *Mitzvah barishon*. But רבי יוסי *Rabbi
Yossi*'s statement ended with saying but if the second one is of
better quality מובחר ממנו *Muvchar mimenu* then you should go with the
second one. So תוספות *Tosafot* asks an interesting question why don't we
say the same on in this scenario where you have two goats
and whatever and you replaced it and fine רב Rav *Rav* says
you want to do the first one but why not say if
the second one is better? So that's תוספות *Tosafot*'s question. So you
know you would have asked me I would have said the answer
is how could the second one be better they're supposed to be
the same?
But they're only supposed to be the same when you did the
original pairing. Remember this is based on a second pair so it's
possible that the second pair is better. So why not mention that?
So look at this little תוספות *Tosafot* we'll start with this on
ס"ד עמוד ב' *Samech Dalet Amud Bet*. ואם השני מובחר ממנו יביאנו
*V'im hashani muvchar mimenu yavi'enu*, first top little תוספות *Tosafot* on ס"ד
עמוד ב' *Samech Dalet Amud Bet*. תוספות *Tosafot* says ובמתניתין נמי נימא
הכי *U'vmatnisin nami neima hachi*.
So the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* you know yeah maybe that's also true
by our case of the goats if the second pair is better
maybe you would use it. אי נמי *Ei nami* says תוספות *Tosafot*
maybe לא שייך הך מילתא *lo shayach hach milta* this idea of
go with the better one rather than the first maybe that's not
relevant אלא בגבולין *ela b'gvulin*
only in the גבולין *gvulin*. Now that's a funny word here someone
switched the word to בנאכלים *b'ne'echalim* things that you would eat או
בנעשים בעזרה *o b'na'asim ba'azarah* or things that were done in the
courtyard. אבל בשעיר המשתלח ובשעיר הפנימי *Aval b'se'ir hamisaleach u'vse'ir hapnimi*
by the thing that is not you know going to be eaten
or not eaten in the outside the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beit
HaMikdash* but is going to be sent out right or the opposite
the one that's going to go on the in the holy of
holies הנשרף חוץ לשלושה מחנות *hanisraf chutz l'shlosha machanot* and when it's
burnt it's burnt out of the camp אפילו אם היה שני מובחר
ממנו מצוה mitzvah בראשון *afilu im haya nightmare sheni muvchar mimenu mitzvah
rishon*. Even if the second one is better still stick with the
first. Why do I think this תוספות *Tosafot* is powerful? Because in
the context of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beit HaMikdash* right you're
always dealing with this issue about like why does God care about
all this stuff? Meaning Not korbanot in general, but the whole focus
on aesthetics. It has to be unblemished, it has to be perfect,
it has to be of high quality, right? Don't we want to
be like all the gold and the silver and the כהנים Kohanim...
have to be unblemished and all of this? All of this focus
on the externals, aren't we supposed to think that, you know, what
God wants from us is not the externals? And one sort of
basic answer to that question is, it's true, God doesn't care about
all that stuff. But we as human beings are very influenced by
all of that. And sort of the power that it has to
us, you know, seeing a place that's so beautiful, seeing everything looking
perfect, not marred, you know, that has an impact on our understanding
of it. And if we were to bring a קרבן korban, that
was blemished, or you know, then what would that do to affect
our idea of what is, you know, of the holiness, the elevation
of the place? But it's really a concession for us, it's not
something that God wants. What I think is powerful is that that's
essentially what this תוספות is saying. The idea of choosing the better
one is only a concern for things that are in the human
sphere. So if it's something that you're going to eat or you're
going to see, like it's going to be brought in the עזרה,
azarah, the human beings, the people are going to witness it, experience
it, then we would choose the better one. But if it's something
that's not going to be part of our experience, it's going to
be sent outside of the camp, nobody else is going to sort
of see it, or it's going to be brought inside the קודש
הקדשים, Kodesh Hakodashim, so then why do we care if it's better
or not better? If it's the first one, that sort of thing,
that gets priority, that's more significant than this question about appearances and
quality. So I think there's something really powerful for this in like
a, you know, counter-note to this general idea of how beautiful and
perfect everything has to be, a sort of almost recognition that that's
important when it's something that's within sort of the human, you know,
our context, our experience, but not necessarily something objectively that God cares
about. Yes. Hi Shua. I'm sorry Charlie had his hand up. Yeah.
I might have thought that you'd be even more concerned about quality
for something that is for God.
Yeah, but the point is, quality, yeah, but why is quality defined
as, you know, how fatty it is or how, I mean, meaning
why are these sort of external types of considerations God considerations? Now
you could say because they reflect how much we care, you know,
I understand, I'm saying, yeah, that's normally how you explain it. But
there's something...
I can get away by buying this cheap...
I understand, right, like קין והבל, Kayin v'Hevel, like I'll bring the
non-ideal one. I understand that. But so I, you know, yes, it
ultimately goes back to because of what of it reflects as us
as humans, you know, what it reflects from us. Anyway, I do
think that this is interesting, sort of striking that balance. Okay, let's
get back now to the גמרא. Gemara The גמרא Gemara says like
this.
Okay, so where did we leave off?
תנן. Tnan. Okay, it's now three lines from the bottom. שאין חטאת
ציבור מתה. She'ein chatas tzibur meisa. So now let's go try to
prove the רב ורבי יוחנן Rav v'Rabbi Yochanan debate. Again, רב Rav,
says you use the one from the first pair, מצוה mitzvah בראשון,
and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says that one got rejected, it's דחוי.
dichuy. So let's again try to sort of see which way the
משנה Mishna goes, although we already said the משנה Mishna supports רב
Rav and the ברייתא רבי יהודה. braisa Rabbi Yehuda. So our משנה
Mishna says it again, שאין חטאת ציבור מתה. She'ein chatas tzibur meisa.
So it said, why do you let the other one, whichever the
other one is,
graze and get a blemish and don't let it die? Because that
idea that a חטאת chatas you don't use dies is only according...
is only a private חטאת, chatas, but a communal חטאת chatas does
not die even if it is... you used another one in its
stead. That's what the משנה Mishnah. says. And then רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda disagrees and he says, no, even for a communal חטאת, chatas,
if another one was used in its stead, you let it die.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says הא דיחיד כי האי גוונא
מתה. Ha d'yachid ki hai gavna meisa. The obvious implication of the
משנה Mishna is that the reason this doesn't die is because it's
communal. Were it a private חטאת chatas in a similar scenario, you
would let it die. So let's see which way this works according
to רב Rav, and רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, whether you would let
a private חטאת chatas die.
בשלמא לרבי יוחנן, Bishlama l'Rabbi Yochanan, this works according to
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan כדרבי אבא. k'd'Rabbi Abba. This would be like
רבי אבא. Rabbi Abba. דאמר רבי אבא אמר רב. D'amar Rabbi Abba
amar Rav. דאמר רבי אבא אמר רב, D'amar Rabbi Abba amar Rav,
thank you so much, רבי אבא Rabbi Abba says in the name
of רב, Rav got it, okay, הכל מודים, Hakol modim, דף ס'
עמוד א',
daf samech amud
aleph, all agree שבנתכפר בשאינה אבודה אבודה מתה. she'nitkapar b'she'eina avuda avuda
meisa.
So this is a classic scenario: you have a קרבן, korban a
חטאת chatas sanctified, set aside, and it gets lost. We'll call that
A. And then you go ahead and you sanctify another קרבן korban
B in its stead. And then you're going to bring B. And
then what happens? A shows up before you get a chance to
bring B. Which... and you can choose, which one are you going
to bring, A or B? So this... so he says that there's
a debate if you bring one, like when you... when you bring
one, what would happen if... what would happen to the one left
over? Is
the one
left over
going to die
because it's, you
know.
A got lost, you separated out B, and now you found A.
Which and you're going to bring one of them. So there's a
debate whether the one left over grazes or dies. Okay, so says
רבי אבא Rabbi Abba in the name of רב, Rav everybody agrees
הכל מודים hakol modim שנתכפר בשאינה אבודה, sheniskaper beshe'eina avuda,
that if you use the one that had never been lost, B,
שאבודה מתה. she'avuda mesa. The one that was lost, A, everybody agrees
that's where the הלכה halacha is, that that you'll let die. Okay,
because that was lost, that in a way was already sort of
pushed away to a certain degree. Isn't it? Right? It was right
for this period it couldn't be used. Now it's coming back, you're
choosing B over it, you're pushing, you're further rejecting that, pushing it
away. Everybody agrees in this case when you use B instead, we
say נתכפר באחר, niskaper beacher, when the owners were atoned with with
another one, then this has to be allowed to die. The whole
debate of whether you let it die or not is if you
actually went ahead and you used A. So said that case maybe
B, which had never been lost and never somehow been problematic, maybe
that you would not let die. That's what he says. Why is
that relevant? Because what's our case? So again, he says that if
you use B, in the case where you use B,
then everybody says that this one is going to die. Now what's
our case? Our case you'll remember is you have, right, your two
goats here, or these are two goats, one of them dies, okay,
now you're going to take another lottery, right, and you draw again.
And according to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan which one are you going
to use? You're going to use right this, right? You're going to
use, you know, this, you know, this right or rather, well this
let's say substitutes for that. But you're going to use this one,
right? He says you don't use the other one, that's נדחה. nidcheh,
So that's similar to the idea of, right,
there was an animal already around, you had a replacement, you didn't
use the one that had been around from before. So that's like
this case. You used the new one, you didn't use the old
one. So everybody agrees that the old one, the one that you
didn't use from before is the one you're going to let die.
That's similar to this case. You use the new one. It's maybe
a little hard because
was the old one ever, the old one was never lost.
What? This case, I took, I did the opposite of A and
B. Exactly. So it wasn't, it was visually confusing. Okay, so anyway,
so in this case this was lost, this, and this was the
first one, okay? And everybody agrees that when you use the second
one, he says that the first one is going to let die.
So that works. You use the second one according to רבי יוחנן,
Rebbe Yochanan, the first one you're going to let die. Okay, so
that works. According to רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan in a normal case
like this, where you use the new one and not the old
one, everybody agrees the old one you let die. אלא לרב, ela
le'Rav, but according to רב Rav, says this doesn't work. Why is
it that we would say that in a normal, that this type
of a case had it been in a private scenario, it would
have been that you should let the, that you should let the
animal die? Why? הוי ליה כמפריש שתי חטאות לאחריות. havia lei kemafresh
shtei chatas le'achrayus. It's like you separated out two sin offerings for
backup. I'll explain what this means in a minute. ואמר רבי אושעיא,
ve'amar Rabbi Oshaya, and רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya said, המפריש שתי חטאות
לאחריות, hamafresh shtei chatas le'achrayus, נתכפר באחת מהם, niskaper be'achas mehem, if
you separated two for backup, one you use, והשנייה תרעה, vehashniya tireh,
and the second one grazes, meaning the whole הלכה halacha that when
you use one and reject the, you reject one and use the
other, נתכפר באחר, niskaper beacher, this is by the way the category
for חטאת chatas that dies, it's called נתכפר באחר. niskaper beacher. You
used another one and therefore the one that's left over has to
die. That's only when you started with one and then you had
a replacement because this got lost or whatever. Here there was a
different reason. So you had a replacement, in that case this one
is rejected, it was replaced and therefore it's going to be let
to die. That's in a case of replacement. But there's another scenario.
The other scenario is not a case of a replacement. The other
scenario is a case of where there are alternatives. Not a substitute,
but alternatives. You from the very beginning didn't have an A and
a B, but from the very beginning you said I'm separating out
two animals. You know why? Because I know I always tend to
lose things. I lose my car keys, so I'm afraid I'm going
to lose my sheep also. Okay. And I'm going to separate out
these two animals, sanctify both of them, and I will say, I'll
be able to use one of them for a חטאת, Chatas, and
there'll be backups in case I lose one, I'll have the other
one. So neither is a substitute for the other, they're both around
to be a backup for one another. לאחריות. L'achrayus. Right, they're going,
one is backing the other one up, it's not substituting. In that
case, where it's not that one was originally there and then it
was substituted in, and then we can say, you got something else
to substitute, this one is going to let die. In this case
where they're both for backup, we say you use one for your
חטאת, Chatas, whichever one you use, and the other one we let
graze, because it's not really that this was substituted, it was always
there as a backup, so you don't have this idea that it
dies. So the גמרא Gemara says, according to רב, Rav, that's essentially
what's going on here, because רב Rav, said, here you are,
you took these two new goats, right, while you had this one
died, you had these, you took these two new goats, okay, right?
It's not that one of them you couldn't use. According to רבי
יוחנן, Rebbe Yochanan as soon as this one died, the remaining one
became in a sense
דחויה, Dichuyah, lost, it became like it was אבודה, Avudah, right, like
it was lost, because there was a period you couldn't use it,
and therefore it became rejected. So according to רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan,
that follows the idea that this is a substitute, because this became
rejected. But according to רב, Rav. this was never rejected, this always
remained okay. And not only did it remain okay, it's going to
stay okay. So when you took two new goats, what was the
purpose of this one that wound up being להשם, L'Hashem, right, assuming
that this is להשם? L'Hashem? The purpose of this wasn't that this
was like substituting for the other one, and this wasn't substituting for
it. They were both now theoretically able to be used. It was
never the case that one couldn't be used and the other was
being substituted. The only reason anyway רב Rav, says that you use
this is because of מצוה mitzvah בראשון, that there's a preference to
do the first. But in theory either of them are legitimate. So
it's like you have two things that equally could be used, not
one is substituted for another one that's no longer usable. So the
גמרא Gemara says, why should it even be, you know, why are
we saying that only because it's a communal sacrifice does it not
die? This should be like the case of two animals that are
equally set aside to be used for the same function, that the
other one doesn't die. Okay, there's no one here that's being rejected,
pushed away, unusable and so on. Let's just see the answer. So
the גמרא Gemara says, כיון דאמר רבא, Keivan D'amar Rava, רבא, Rava,
since רבא Rava has explained, here's the answer, that רב סבר לה
כרבי יוסי, Rav savar lah k'Rabbi Yossi, רב Rav, holds like רבי
יוסי, דאמר מצוה בראשון, D'amar Mitzvah B'Rishon, says that the מצוה mitzvah
is in the first one, so maybe it's not absolutely בדיעבד, B'dieved,
but that's basically what you're going to be doing. מעיקרא כמפריש לאיבוד
דמי. Me'ikara k'mafrish l'ibud dami.
So it says look, since in the end I know that I'm
going to be using this one, so then as soon as I
designate this להשם, L'Hashem, I'm basically saying I'm not going to use
it, because I only did this whole thing in order to get
the one לעזאזל la'azazel to substitute, right? But this one, it's not
like מפריש לאחריות, Mafrish l'achrayus, it's not like I have two legitimate
ones that I can use and I get to choose which one.
I know I'm going to be using this one. So this one
from the very beginning is like separated out to be lost. It's
like designated as not usable. And since it was never really seen
as usable, that's like the case of one that is lost, and
therefore that one actually would die. And that's why had it not,
that's why had it been in the case of a private חטאת,
Chatas, this would be like one that is lost, because this one
was never seen as usable. And that's why only because it's a
communal sacrifice is it not that it dies, but that it's left
to graze.
לאחריות L'achrayus is the same thing. Just like you know when you
do the אחריות, achrayus, you really want to use both of them,
especially here where you're really trying to keep.
That's exactly what the גמרא Gemara says, when you separate two לאחריות,
L'achrayus, you really conceive of the possibility that maybe I'll use one,
maybe I'll use the other. Here one of them from the very
beginning, you had to go through the ritual, but you were never
planning on using it. Right. So that's exactly what the גמרא Gemara
says, right?
I just find it interesting that in this entire מחלוקת, machlokes, the
focus is always on identifying the set according to its function, לעזאזל
l'Azazel or להשם, L'Hashem,
and never horizontally as you've drawn it, in other words in terms
of its בן זוג. ben zug.
Right, so that is worth pointing out, that according to, you know,
רב, Rav who says מצוה mitzvah בראשון, right, again, according to רבי
יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan, it's fine, you use two new ones, you use
exactly the pair, if there's even a reason not to use this,
it's נדחה, nidcha, stigmatized, it's pushed away. According to רב, Rav where
you can theoretically choose which one and you only do the first
because it was there first and because it got the label first,
we should point out that the strangeness of this is that the
two goats you're using have never been paired in the same, right,
the lot has not, each one has had a lottery but a
different lottery, and that
is. So you lose all of that sense of the equal, pairing
of the two, correct.
Just between left to graze and left to die.
So left to die means that you like literally don't feed it
and you wait for it to die. Left to graze means you
take care of it, you feed it, whatever. It could live a
nice long life, but because that is
dangerous, הלכתית *halachically*, to leave an animal like that around grazing without
whatever, so you wait until it gets like a blemish and you
then you transfer the sanctity and so on. But left to die
really means like you don't feed it or anything, you just let
it die.
Okay. Alright, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Where were we?
תנן *Tnan*. So now let's try again from the משנה Mishna, *Mishna*
to figure out which way it's going. רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda
Omer, *Rabbi Yehuda omer* ימות *yamut*. So רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda *Rabbi
Yehuda* says, okay, whichever one you're not using, and we saw already
yesterday that he might disagree which one you're not using, but whichever
one you're not using you don't let it graze and then transfer
the קדושה kedushah *kedusha* as we just said. You actually let it
die because he says the same thing you would say by a
private קרבן korban חטאת chatas *korban chatat*, you say by a communal
one. So let's see if this works. בשלמא לרבי יוחנן *Bishlama le-Rabbi
Yochanan*, I get it according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, *Rabbi Yochanan*
that the one you're not using is the one from the first
pair, דאמר שני שבזוג ראשון ירעה *de-amar sheni she-bezug rishon yireh*, that
says that according to the rabbis it's the second one from the
first pair that you would let graze, that's the one you're not
using, רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda ימות *Rabbi Yehuda yamut*, so רבי יהודה
Rebbe Yehuda's *Rabbi Yehuda*, you let it die. מתכפר בשני שבזוג שני
*mitkaper be-sheni she-bezug sheni*, and which one are you left to use?
The second one from the second pair. Fine. אלא לרב דאמר שני
שבזוג שני ירעה *Ela le-Rav de-amar sheni she-bezug sheni yireh*, for according
to רב *Rav* according to the rabbis, he says that this is
the one you let graze and you go back and you use
the first one. So לרבי יהודה ימות *le-Rabbi Yehuda yamut*, and רבי
יהודה Rebbe Yehuda's *Rabbi Yehuda* says it dies, לרבי יהודה במה מתכפר
*le-Rabbi Yehuda bameh mitkaper*? What animal's going to be left to you?
What does that mean? It means the following. Remember what we said
yesterday. Yesterday we said that רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* says
נשפך הדם ימות המשתלח *nishpach ha-dam yamut ha-mishtaleach*, if the blood spills
the one that's to be sent off dies, and the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* proves from there that רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* is
like the position that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* said of
בעלי חיים נדחין baalei chayim nidchin, *baalei chayim nidchin*. If the blood
spills the animal you were going to send off has to let
die, meaning that there is this idea that even though it was
alive it gets pushed away and becomes unusable. You remember that from
yesterday that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said that רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda
*Rabbi Yehuda* would say בעלי חיים נדחין baalei chayim nidchin. *baalei chayim
nidchin*, that's how he was arguing with רב *Rav*. So if רב
*Rav* says בעלי חיים נדחין baalei chayim nidchin, *baalei chayim nidchin*, so
if רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* says that, so in this
scenario one dies, רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda *Rabbi
Yehuda* would say this one has to be, has to die, because
בעלי חיים נדחין baalei chayim nidchin. *baalei chayim nidchin*. Then you take
a new pair. Okay people with me here? So you take a
new pair. Okay so this is going to be... this you've got.
Now what do you do with it? Okay so here's the thing.
According to רב *Rav*,
let me get this straight. One minute. According to
רב *Rav*, רב *Rav* says מצוה mitzvah בראשון *mitzvah be-rishon*, so you're
going to use that... Right. Okay. So רב *Rav*, so this is
the scenario. You got this new pair. You're going to use this
one... is going to be לעזאזל l'Azazel *la-Azazel*. So רב *Rav* would
say which one grazes of these two? Do you remember what רב
*Rav* says? רב *Rav* says מצוה mitzvah בראשון *mitzvah be-rishon*, so which
one is going to graze? The second one. This is going to
graze. So we assume that the same one the rabbis say is
going to graze, רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* is going to
say... we assume they're talking about the same animal. So the rabbis
say let this one graze, so we assume רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda
*Rabbi Yehuda* is going to say die. But now we've got a
problem because we learned from before that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi
Yehuda* holds בעלי חיים נדחין ba'alei chayim nidchin. *baalei chayim nidchin*. So
he also held that this one was going to die. So if
this one is going to die because of בעלי חיים נדחין ba'alei
chayim nidchin. *baalei chayim nidchin* and this is the one the rabbis
say will graze and he presumably is talking about the same animal
is going to say die, so now he's saying they're both going
to die. So which one are you going to use? Okay is
everybody thoroughly confused now? Okay you got it?
There's a סתירה *stira* between מצוה mitzvah בראשון *mitzvah be-rishon* and בעלי
חיים נדחין ba'alei chayim nidchin. *baalei chayim nidchin*.
No I'm not telling you that. I'm just saying... no there's an
easy answer. You know what let's see the answer and then maybe
even the question becomes clearer. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says מי
סברת רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אשני שבזוג שני קאי *mi savrat Rabbi
Yehuda a-sheni she-bezug sheni ka-i*? What makes you think we're talking about
the same animal? That just because the rabbis say the second one
of the second group is the one that grazes and the rabbis
want to use the first one, what makes you think that רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehuda* when he says it dies is talking
about the same animal? At the second group. No, רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda. השני שבזוג ראשון קאי. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is talking about
the second one from the first group. Okay. Yeah, meaning the basic
difference is that it’s not they’re talking about the same thing, meaning
the Rabbis say, what do the Rabbis say? The Rabbis say this
one use, cause it’s the first one, and this one graze. What
does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda say? What’s, that’s the Rabbis’ approach. We’ll
use the green. What’s רבי יהודה’s Rabbi Yehuda, approach? רבי יהודה’s Rabbi
Yehudah approach is this one dies, because he holds בעלי חיים נדחין,
ba'alei chayim nidchin. right? That you learned that yesterday. The blood is
spilled, the משתלח mishtale'ach dies. He holds בעלי חיים נדחין. nidchin, And
this one he would say use, right? That’s what רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehudah would say. He argues in two ways. Number one, he says
dies rather than graze, right? Cause even though it’s communal. And number
two is he reverses which animal it is, because he says בעלי
חיים נדחין, nidchin this dies and that one use. So the גמרא
Gemara just says, just cause he says dies doesn’t mean he’s talking
about this one. Right? The גמרא Gemara thought he said this dies
and this dies and there’s nothing left to use. No, he says
dies, but he’s not talking about the same animal that the Rabbis
are talking
about. Pushed away and can’t be, once they stop being able to
be used, they can’t be used in the future. Okay. Where does
מצווה בראשון mitzvah barishon come into this?
If you don’t say נדחין, then you theoretically could use either. What
makes you pick this one? Only the concept of מצווה בראשון. mitzvah
barishon. In theory you could have a position that you’re free to
choose either. As long as it’s not been pushed out, you should
use this cause it’s paired with the other one. All right, so
all of that was a little bit confusing, but the basic point
was, just cause he says dies, we know he says the first
one dies. Just cause he says dies when the Rabbis say graze
doesn’t mean he’s talking about the same animal, then both of them
would die. Okay. הגמרא Hagemara says ואיכא דקא מותיב לה הכי. Ve'ika
deka motiv lah hachi. Some ask it this way: ועוד אמר רבי
יהודה נשפך הדם ימות המשתלח מת המשתלח ישפך הדם. Ve'od amar Rebbe
Yehuda nishpach hadam yamut hamishtale'ach mes hamishtale'ach yishapech hadam. So that’s what
we saw yesterday, that if the blood spills, the one being sent
away has to die, if the one that’s being sent away dies,
the then you have to spill the blood. So the second part
we get, if the one being sent away dies, and they have
to remain paired until the blood is offered up, then its blood
was נדחה, nidcha. was became unusable. But the fact that he says
if the blood spills the משתלח mishtale'ach dies proves this idea that
בעלי חיים נדחין. If for a period the live animal couldn’t be
used, it remains unusable. So בשלמא לרב רישא פליגי בחטאת ציבור וסיפא
פליגי בבעלי חיים. Bishlama leRav reisha pligi bechatas tzibbur vesayfa pligi bebaalei
chayim. This is what the גמרא Gemara. said yesterday. We understand the
two issues that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is debating about. Issue number
one is, does a communal חטאת chatas graze or does it die?
Issue number two is, which animal do you use? Do you hold
that a live animal can be pushed off or not? אלא לרבי
יוחנן מאי ועוד? Ela leRebbe Yochanan mai ve'od? According to רבי יוחנן,
there’s no two debates, there’s only one point. הגמרא Hagemara says קשיא.
Kashya. You’re right, it’s difficult. So again, what’s the point? The point
is, as I just showed you over here, that according to רב,
there’s two principles. Number one is you use the first one, which
shows בעלי חיים
אינם נדחין. baalei chayim einam nidchin. You know, it does not get
pushed away. You use the first one and the second one grazes,
which is that a חטאת ציבור chatas tzibbur is תרעה, tireh, does
not die. That’s the position of the חכמים. Chachamim. Comes along רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda? and he disagrees both. First רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says תמות, tamus, that a חטאת ציבור chatas tzibbur dies even though
it’s a חטאת ציבור, chatas tzibbur, the one you’re not going to
use is died. ועוד אמר רבי יהודה, Ve'od amar Rebbe Yehuda, and
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. also said that once something becomes unusable, it
gets pushed away. בעלי חיים is נדחה. nidcha. This one is the
one that gets rejected. בעלי חיים, even though it was alive, it’s
נדחה. nidcheh, This is the one that you’re going to use. So
he had two points of argument. That works according to רב. He
argues on two things. But remember, רבי יוחנן also said this one
doesn’t get
used. רבי יוחנן also said בעלי חיים נדחה. baalei chayim nidcha. So
according to רבי יוחנן, what are the two points that רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda debates? He’s really only arguing one thing, whether it dies
or grazes. But the issue that the one that’s left behind is
the one that dies, that’s every, that would be agreed upon. And
the גמרא Gemara admits that that is not clear according to רבי
יוחנן, what is the second point that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda disagrees
with.
I’ve forgotten what the criteria are for distinguishing between whether you say
graze or die.
Well, the type of a חטאת chatas, that, a private חטאת, chatas
there are five scenarios where a private חטאת chatas, has to let
die, is basically all the scenarios in which you can’t use it,
which is: if the owners died, if it’s a ולד חטאת, velad
chatas, if it gave birth, if it’s a תמורת חטאת, temuras chatas,
if נתכפרו בעליו באחרת, niscapru ba'alav beacheres, which is what we’re talking
about, they, it got lost, they used a different קרבן korban and
they used a substitute, and if it became more than a year
old. So in any of those five scenarios, you have to let
it die. But if that happens at a communal חטאת, chatas the
חכמים Chachamim say. you let it graze, you let it get a
blemish, you redeem it, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says I don't
make any distinction. A communal one will also be let die.
בין יחיד ובין ציבור. bein yachid ubein tzibbur.
And the ציבור, tzibbur, exactly. That is the basic position. So the
גמרא Gemara says חטאת ציבור chattas tzibbur as opposed to חטאת יחיד.
chattas yachid. That's the issue. That the rabbis say חטאת ציבור chattas
tzibbur is treated differently. So that clearly is the debate in the
משנה. Mishna. The question is when רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda? gives the
scenario of the blood is spilled, let the משלח mishaleach die, משלח
mishaleach was spilled, what's the new point he's making
there? So according to רב, the new point he's making is that
בעלי חיים נדחין. That even though the animal is alive, the blood
spilled, the other one's alive, the one that's alive can no longer
be used, it has to be pushed away. So according to רב,
that's a position that's different from the חכמים. chachamim. But according to
רבי יוחנן, רבי יוחנן said that's what the חכמים chachamim hold. That
all בעלי חיים נדחין. So what's the second debate? Yes.
Well, isn't he just saying really that because they're נדחין therefore...
Yeah, but the ועוד v'od suggests that it's a second issue. That's
why the גמרא Gemara didn't say it's a complete contradiction. It said
קשיא, kashya, but it sounds like it's a second debate. Okay, now
we get to move on. So a little confusing there, but I
think you got it mostly. So now we move on. ועוד אמר
רבי יהודה נשפך הדם ימות המשלח. Ve'od amar Rabbi Yehuda, nishpach hadam
yamut hamishaleach.
So now we get exactly to the second point. If the blood
spills, the one that's going to be sent away has to be
let die. That's the principle of בעלי חיים נדחין. There's a period
you can't use the משלח mishaleach because the משלח, mishaleach, you only
send the one away לעזאזל l'Azazel.
after the blood procedure is done. So if the blood spills, then
there's a period where this is not usable right now because we
have to get a whole new קרבן korban or whatever. Everything is
being held in abeyance. So the point that right now it's unusable
because the blood spilled makes it נדחה, nidcheh pushed away. And that's
the principle בעלי חיים נדחין. That's what we've been saying, at least
according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda חכמים chachamim maybe not, but at
least according to רבי יהודה. But what's the other idea? If the
משלח mishaleach dies, you have to spill the blood. Why do you
have to spill the blood just because the משלח mishaleach dies? Why
did, why does the blood require that the משלח mishaleach still be
alive? Okay, so let's take a look. So what the גמרא Gemara
says: בשלמא נשפך הדם ימות המשלח. Bisheleima nishpach hadam yamut hamishaleach.
I get when the blood spills, the משלח mishaleach has to be
let die. דאכתי לא עביד מצותו. de'aketi lo avid mitzvato.
You haven't yet done the מצוה mitzvah with it. The מצוה mitzvah.
is, right, that the blood has to be put on the altar.
The מצוה mitzvah. hasn't yet been done. So the משלח mishaleach is
not yet ready to be sent off and therefore it's נדחה when
the blood is spilled because the מצוה mitzvah hasn't been done yet.
אלא מת המשלח אמאי ישפך הדם? Ella met hamishaleach, amai yishapech hadam?
Just because the משלח mishaleach dies, why does the blood have to
be spilled? הא עביד ליה מצותו. Ha avid lei mitzvato. The מצוה
mitzvah, was done. Really? What מצוה mitzvah. did you finish? You got
blood and you got a live goat. What מצוה did you finish?
You didn't put the blood on the altar. You didn't send the
goat away. So if you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י
Rashi says something quite shocking. Let's take a look at רש"י. Rashi.
He says like this:
two lines down in the medium-sized lines, last word in the line.
אלא מת המשלח למה לא תשלומין שאתה מזקיק כזה להביא לו שנים
ולהגריל וישפך דם ראשון? Ella met hamishaleach, lama lo tashlumin she'ata mazki
kachazeh lehavi lo shnayim ulehagril veyishpach dam rishon? Why do you have
to get another goat just because the משלח mishaleach died? הא עביד
מצותו. Ha avid mitzvato. How has the מצוה been done for the
live goat? דשיר משלח כל דבר מעכב בו אינה אלא הגרלה בלבד.
deshir mishaleach, kol davar me'akev bo eina ela hagrala bilvad.
You basically have finished the מצוה once you've done the lot. לקבוע
גורל על זה שם על זה לא. likboa goral al zeh shem,
al zeh lo. How do you know? דהא שמעינן ליה לרבי יהודה,
deha shem im lei leRabbi Yehuda, we know that רבי יהודה holds
דאמר לא התודה כשר. de'amar lo hitvadah kasher. We know from an
earlier סוגיא sugya you might remember that רבי יהודה says even if
you didn't do the וידוי viduy it's כשר. kasher. And now רש"י
Rashi says not only you didn't do the וידוי viduy it's כשר,
kasher, דכל שכן דשילוח דלא מעכב. dechol sheken deshiluach d'lo me'akev.
Even sending it out isn't מעכב. me'akev. You believe that? So בדיעבד,
bedi'eved, as soon as you drew the lot, you don't have to
do... בדיעבד, bedi'eved, if you didn't do the וידוי, viduy, you didn't
send it off, it dropped dead, you are יוצא yotzei the מצוה.
You don't push off the cliff, you don't do anything, it's dropped
dead, you're יוצא yotzei the מצוה. Okay, דברי הכל, de'divrei hakol, and
why is it not
מעכב? me'akev? דכתיב, dechi ksiv, remember this, חוקה, chukka, remember the whole
idea of חוק chok and where order matters? So רש"י Rashi says
not just where order matters, it's where even the thing itself matters.
הדם שכהן עושה בבגדי לבן. hadam shekohein oseh bivgadei lavan.
It's only at maximum things that are done with the white garments.
ולא דברים הנעשים על ידי איש עתי, velo dvarim hana'asim al yedei
ish iti, not the one done by the other guy who runs
it off the cliff. So look at this amazing thing. We so
focus on the goat going off the cliff and are בדיעבד bedi'eved
if you didn't do it, it's fine, you're יוצא yotzei anyway. At
most, maybe it's the וידוי viduy that's מעכב. me'akev. But even that,
according to רבי יהודה, not.
So it's really powerful that the central symbolism is simply the drawing
of the lot. Right, that's huge.
Right,
like looking to clear everything else away to allow the הגרלה hagrala
to be merged as absolutely central. It's exactly...
Yeah, it's
like a really fatalistic...
It is, it is. Right. But I... But I would also say
according to חז״ל Chazal again remember we had before about how much
they focused that the וידוי viduy of the שעיר se'ir is it's
not the blood of the שעיר, se'ir, it's not the off the
cliff, it's the וידוי viduy that creates the כפרה. kaparah. So according
to the חכמים Chachamim at least you understand, pushing it off the
cliff isn't what's necessary, the וידוי viduy is what's necessary, and that
really focuses us on like I said, transitions us to a post
מקדש mikdash reality that it's all about תשובה teshuvah and וידוי viduy
and so on. But according to רבי יהודה it's not even that,
it's just the הגרלה. hagralah. So the גמרא Gemara says I don't
understand, you did the
הגרלה, hagralah, you did the הגרלה, hagralah, the שעיר se'ir dropped dead,
who cares? You have nothing left to do with this שעיר, se'ir,
so why should you care that it dropped dead? So big deal,
why do you need to do it again? So let's just see
the answer that they take the question, so the גמרא Gemara says
אמר דבי רבי ינאי amar d'bei Rabbi Yannai אמר קרא amar kra
because the verse says יעמד חי, ya'amad chai, והשעיר אשר עליו עלה
הגורל הזה יעמד חי לפני ה׳ לכפר עליו, v'hase'ir asher alav ala
hagoral hazeh ya'amad chai lifnei Hashem l'chaper alav, should remain standing before
God to atone on it. עד מתי יהא זקוק להיות חי? ad
matai yehei zakuk l'hiyot chai? How long does that goat have to
remain alive? עד שעת מתן דמי של חברו. ad sha'at matan dami
shel chaveiro. יעמד חי ya'amad chai until לכפר עליו, l'chaper alav, until
you use the other blood, the other goat to do the atonement.
So it says logically you're right, logically it's not that there's any
מצוה left to be done בדיעבד b'diavad with this goat. Okay, the
goat could drop dead. But the only thing is the תורה Torah
demands that it remains alive while the atonement of the other goat
is taking place. And that's also you know this idea of sort
of designating they're different. This one has to be standing לעזאזל la-Azazel,
while this one is going לה׳. l'Hashem. After this one goes לה׳,
l'Hashem, the other one could drop dead without a וידוי, viduy, without
being sent off, fine, that doesn't matter. But what is required is
that during the process that this blood is going on, this have
to be standing. So if this one drops dead, even though בדיעבד
b'diavad you don't need the וידוי viduy and you don't need it
off the cliff, you need it to be alive and around while
you're doing it. So therefore you need to take another goat and
do another lottery in order that you have a live goat standing
לעזאזל la-Azazel, while you do the עבודה. avodah.
But if it drops dead you still don't have to worry about
you know getting another one to send it off?
Exactly. But you do need another one alive while you're doing the
עבודה avodah of the blood. Rivky, you had a question?
I was just going to say, stay alive while back in the
day to take the to help and carry the sins of the
people of Israel away from the טומאת מקדש...
tumat mikdash... Yes, yes. Atonement for the כהנים...
And well
also for the one sin of טומאת מקדש. tumat mikdash. The goat
on the inside is the one sin of טומאת מקדש.
tumat mikdash. So when they get sent away and carry...
Right, exactly.
So I would assume they would want it to get sent away.
And it's so clear in the תורה, Torah, so my I'm thinking
maybe they're so uncomfortable with the עזאזל... Azazel...
So I was wondering about that too, that by saying בדיעבד b'diavad
you don't need it to go on the cliff also deals with
some of that whole problematics of what does it mean to be
sending it לעזאזל. la-Azazel, I completely agree. But at least it's a
lot better, I completely agree. Right, עזאזל, Azazel, you know, you do,
but it doesn't really matter, it's not really what's important. Exactly, it's
all matters what goes on in the מקדש. mikdash. I completely agree.
But again, it is it's better, you know, it makes more sense
if you at least demand that there's also a וידוי, viduy, because
then you understand at least the power of the וידוי viduy affects
the atonement. רבי יהודה doesn't even require וידוי, viduy, like, what are
you left with? You know, but I agree that by saying you
don't need it off the cliff deals with the עזאזל Azazel problem.
It takes away all the drama.
It certainly does.
But you know, what you just said, Rabbi Winzer, reminds me the
way the חכמים Chachamim also dealt with the נחש הנחשת. nechash hanechoshet.
Right, exactly.
In
other words, yeah, the copper snake.
It's not really what's doing it. Right, it's that their כוונה kavanah
and whatever.
Right, it only looks like...
Exactly. Exactly. Just very quickly, got to move. Yeah.
Were we also entertaining whether we even needed הגרלה hagralah to begin
with at some point earlier?
Yeah, we were entertaining whether we needed the הנחה hanachah was מעכב.
me'akev. Oh, was it? Also entertained there was also the possibility whether
the הגרלה hagralah was מעכב. me'akev. You still might have needed the
designation, but possibly without the act of הגרלה. hagralah.
You might not have had הגרלה.
hagralah. You would have... Right. And we had the position of רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says that you can pair if one drops
dead you can pair the other one without a הגרלה. hagralah.
Right, so it means so almost everything...
But there at least you had a הגרלה hagralah take place. But
yeah, it's a good point. Right. Okay, so let's go back to
the גמרא. Gemara's תנן התם. tnan hatam. All right, now it gets
a little bit easier and a little bit more and like I
think you know interesting from a different perspective. Okay. So this might
be familiar if you remember from שקלים. Shekalim. בני העיר ששלחו את
שקליהם, b'nei ha'ir sheshalechu et shkaleichem, cities send their whole, a village
sends all of the שקלים shkalim that they raised for this year,
right, for the new קרבנות, korbanot, ונגנבו או שאבדו, v'nignevu o she'avedu,
and they got and they got held up, they got robbed, the
people that were bringing the שקלים shkalim to the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash, or the money got lost.
So is it considered like they already paid their taxes or not?
You know, they already paid their שקל. shekel. At what point is
it considered like they've paid their שקל? shekel? So אם נתרמה התרומה,
im nitrmah hatrumah, if this event occurred, it got lost or they
got robbed after the תרומה trumah was taken. Remember what happens, three
times in the year... all of the שקלים Shkalim that go to
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash there's this תרומה, Truma, this ritual lifting
up of, you know, sort of scooping out of the baskets from
the room that's filled with the שקלים Shkalim to use some of
those שקלים, Shkalim, a new sort of removal of the money in
order to use it to buy the קרבנות. Korbanot. That's taking the
תרומה. Truma. They went with baskets, they filled it up from the
room that had all the שקלים Shkalim and that was considered taking
the תרומה, Truma, תרומת הלשכה. Trumat HaLishka. That act said that at
that moment any money that has now been given, even if it
hasn't, even if it's not yet in this room, even if it's
en route, it's considered to have been given. It's considered that it's
been paid. Okay, so at the moment that the תרומה Truma was
taken, any moneys that had been donated even if they had not
yet made it to the room yet were already considered registered and
paid. So if it got lost and stolen after the תרומה Truma
was taken, fine, they've paid their taxes, they've paid their שקל, Shekel,
they're off the hook.
Okay?
So אם נתרמה תרומה נשבעין לגזברין, Im nitruma truma nishba'in l'gizbarin, then
the people that were bringing the money have to take an oath
to the owners, to the treasurers of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
you know, they didn't put it in their own pocket, they weren't
negligent, so that's the ones that they're liable to because it's the
בית המקדש that has lost out, so they make an oath that
they weren't negligent and then the city is off the hook because
the city has paid their שקל. Shekel. ואם לאו, V'im lav, but
if it got stolen or lost before the תרומה Truma was taken,
then their donation has not yet been officially paid. Then the city
still owes their שקל Shekel and the people that lost it, they
have to, they have to sort of
own up, their responsibility is towards the city people. So then נשבעין
לבני העיר, nishba'in livnei ha'ir, they have to swear to the city
people that they weren't negligent, ובני העיר u'vnei ha'ir and the people
of the city, they're left holding the bag. They are literally שוקלין
אחרים תחתיהם, shoklin acheirim tachteihem, they have to give another שקל. Shekel.
Okay, so that's a fascinating question which is at what stage is
it considered like the שקל Shekel had been given. Now we have
another point. נמצאו, Nimtzu,
now after they paid a second שקל, Shekel, they found the lost
שקלים. Shkalim. או שהחזירו גנבים, O shehechziru gannavim, or they actually caught
the robbers, and now they have two sets of שקלים. Shkalim. They
gave the first one and they actually already gave the second one.
So what do they do? Can they use
the second amount towards next year's שקל? Shekel? Prepay your taxes, prepay
your שקל. Shekel. So what's the הלכה? halacha? אלו ואלו שקלים הן,
Elu v'elu Shkalim hen,
so the first position in the משנה is they both are שקלים,
Shkalim, they both go to this year's שקל, Shekel, ואין עולים להם
לשנה הבאה, v'ein olim lahem l'shana haba'ah, I'm sorry, you can't use
it towards next year's שקל, Shekel, you'll just write it off as
another donation to the בית המקדש, but that's it, you're stuck.
Okay, what is possible?
רבי יהודה אומר, רבי יהודה says עולים להם לשנה הבאה, olim lahem
l'shana haba'ah, you know what, you can use it for next year's
שקל. Shekel. מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה? Mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Yehuda? What's the
reason of רבי יהודה? אמר רבא, Amar Rava, קסבר רבי יהודה, kasavar
Rabbi Yehuda, חובת השנה הזו קרבה לשנה הבאה, chovas hashana hazo kreiva
l'shana haba'ah, that even something that was given for an obligation for
this year, if it wasn't used for this year, it could be
used for next year. So now you might see where the גמרא
Gemara is going. Something that wasn't used for this year could be
used for next year. What happens in our case? Our case is
you took another קרבנות, Korbanot, another pair, right, you're going to use
it because I don't know, the blood got spilled, you're going to
use the new pair. So רבי יהודה says what do you do
with the original משתלח? mishtalei'ach? You let it die. So now we
have a question. What's the question? Why do you let it die?
Why not use it for next year? Okay, right, oh, so the
גמרא Gemara is going to get to that, okay, but this about
whether it's too old. The שעיר sa'ir has to be one year,
and it's going to be too old. It's funny how long it
takes the גמרא Gemara to get to that situation. Okay, but let's
take a look. But it's going to have another question where it
doesn't have as easy of an answer because it's going to deal
with a similar case by the ox and an ox can be
up to three years. Okay, so let's take a look. So that's
the position of רבי יהודה. You can use it towards next year.
So איתיבי אביי, eisvei Abaye, so אביי Abaye asked on this, פר
ושעיר של יום הכפורים, par v'sa'ir shel Yom HaKippurim, you know, not
even for our משנה, let's go with a much more general משנה.
If you have the ox or the goat of יום כיפור Yom
Kippur. שאבדו, she'avdu, they got lost, והפריש אחרים תחתיהם, v'hifrishi acheirim tachteihem,
and now you've set aside a new one, a substitute, וכן שעירי
עבודה זרה v'hen se'irei avoda zara שאבדו, she'avdu, or goats that would
be brought if the whole ציבור tzibur sinned by עבודה זרה, avoda
zara, and they would bring this communal חטאת chatas of a goat
and it got lost and והפריש אחרים תחתיהם, v'hifrish acheirim tachteihem, and
you put a substitute, כולם ימותו, kulam yamutu, and then you found
the old one, so you have to let the old ones die.
You know, or the new ones die, one of them dies. Whichever
one you're not using dies. That goes to a question of נדחי,
nidchei, but it doesn't matter which one dies, one of them is
going to die. דברי רבי יהודה, Divrei Rabbi Yehuda, that's what רבי
יהודה says. So remember רבי יהודה says even a חטאת ציבור... chatas
tzibur... that isn't used dies. That's one of the debates. רבי יהודה
says dies. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon אומרים, omrim,
ירעה עד שיסתאב. yera ad sheyistaveu. No, they say that would be
true if it was a private חטאת chatas, because it's a communal
חטאת, chatas you let it graze and it get a blemish, וימכר
ויפלו דמיו לנדבה, veyimacher veyipelu damav linedavah, and use the proceeds, you
transfer the קדושה to money and use the proceeds to buy a
free will עולה, olah, שאין חטאת ציבור מתה, she'ein chatas tzibur meisah,
because a communal חטאת doesn't die, it's allowed to graze. So that's
the classic debate, graze or die. But now we've got a question,
why die according to רבי יהודה? Just hold on to it and
use it for next year's יום כיפור. Yom Kippur Okay, why does
he make it die? ואמר ליה, Va'amar lei, so he said back
to him, Is this אילו של עבודה זרה? ailo shel Avodah Zarah?
Is this אילו של עבודה זרה? ailo shel Avodah Zarah? I could
see that. Fine, so we ask by the יום כיפור Yom Kippur,
case, whatever. But the יום כיפור, Yom Kippur why if you had
substituted an ox or goat, do you let one of them die?
Just hold on to it to next year. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
קרבנות ציבור קאמרת? korbanot tzibur ka'amart? Well wait, you're talking about communal
sacrifices. שאני קרבנות ציבור כדרב טבי אמר רב אמר רבי יאשיה, shani
korbanot tzibur kideRav Tavi amar Rav amar Rabbi Yoshiya, communal sacrifice is
different like רב טבי Rav Tavi says in the name of רב
in the name of רבי יאשיה. Rabbi Yoshiya. דאמר רב טבי אמר
רב אמר רבי יאשיה, De'amar Rav Tavi amar Rav amar Rabbi Yoshiya,
רב טבי Rav Tavi says in the name of רב in the
name of רבי יאשיה, Rabbi Yoshiya, אמר קרא, amar kra, the verse
says, זאת עלת החדש בחדשו, zos olas hachodesh bechodsho, this is the
burnt offering of each month by its month, okay, that's the you
know one you bring on ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. אמר תורה, Amar
torah, the Torah says, חדש והביא לי קרבן מתרומה חדשה. chadesh vehavi
li korban mitrumah chadashah. Okay, renew and bring me a קרבן korban.
from the new donations. Okay, so what does that mean? So what
he's saying is that yes, it's one thing to say apparently that
if you have the money you can use the money towards next
year's money. But if you actually bought a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur
with this year's money, then that קרבן korban, gets designated as a
this year קרבן. korban It's a 5774 קרבן, korban okay, because the
whole idea is you take a new תרומה trumah each year, a
new donation of שקלים shekalim each year for that year's קרבנות. korbanos.
So it's one thing to say when still in the money state
you can advance the money towards next, but if it was bought
with this year's money it's a 5774 קרבן korban and you can't
use it for 5775 and that's the explanation. That's why you can't
use it for next year. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says wait
a minute, התינח שעיר, Hatenach sa'ir, that explains why you can't use
the goat of יום כיפור Yom Kippur? for next year, but פר
מאי איכא למימר? par mai ika lemeimar? How about the ox? Why
is that different? Because whose ox is it? Whose ox is the
ox of יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? The כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. It
comes from his money. It doesn't come from the תרומת הלשכה, trumat
halishkah, it doesn't come from communal funds. So why not use that
for next year? That's point number one, we still have our question,
and number two, גזירה פר אטו שעיר. gezeirah par atu sa'ir. No,
we say that if it happened by the ox you have to
let the ox die because even though you could use it next
year because we're afraid you'll come to do the same thing by
the goat and in the case for the goat it would have
to die because you can't use last year's goat for this year.
So the גמרא Gemara doesn't buy that. First of all the גמרא
Gemara says ומשום גזירה ימותו? umishum gezeirah yamusu? Just because of a
concern you might mix the ox up with the goat if something
similar happened with the goat you're going to let it die? I
mean that's a little drastic, number one. ועוד, Ve'od, and number two,
הא דרב טבי אמר רב אמר רבי יאשיה גופא מצוה היא. ha
deRav Tavi amar Rav amar Rabbi Yoshiya gufa mitzvah hi. The whole
idea of this year's קרבן korban from this year's money is only
a לכתחילה, lechatchilah, it's only a מצוה, it's not בדיעבד. bediavad. דאמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל, De'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, because רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda said in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, קרבנות ציבור הבאין
באחד בניסן, korbanot tzibur haba'in be'echad b'Nisan, once it's ראש חודש ניסן
Rosh Chodesh Nisan we define that the new year for קרבנות korbanos
is ניסן Nisan not תשרי Tishrei and you remember all of the
תקנת שקלים takanat shekalim is in אדר Adar and whatever is so
that you have the funds for ראש חודש ניסן Rosh Chodesh Nisan
for the new years. So if you have now your first new
קרבן of the new year of ראש חודש ניסן, Rosh Chodesh Nisan,
מצוה להביא מן החדש, mitzvah lehavi min hachadash, you should buy this
animal from the new monies. ואם הביא מן הישן, Ve'im hevi min
hayashan, but בדיעבד bediavad if you bought the animal in ניסן Nisan
the communal sacrifice in ניסן Nisan from last year's monies, יצא, yatza,
you fulfilled your obligation. אלא שחיסר מצוה, Ela shechisar mitzvah, you just
lost out a מצוה. לכתחילה Lechatchilah you're not supposed to but בדיעבד
bediavad it's fine. So you don't have any answer. The ox number
one is not a communal sacrifice and don't tell me גזירה gezeirah
because that's a little drastic for גזירה gezeirah to say it dies.
And even the goat even though they were bought with last year's
funds בדיעבד bediavad a 5774 קרבן can be used in 5775. So
you still haven't answered me why you have to let these animals
die. Right, according to רבי יהודה that something that you did for
last year's obligation can be repurposed for this year's obligation, why not
just hold it over till next יום כיפור? Yom Kippur Okay, very
reasonable question. So let's see the גמרא's Gemara answer. אלא אמר רב
זירא, Ela amar Rav Zeira, said רב זירא, Rav Zeira, לפי שאין
הגורל קובע משנה לחברתה. lefi she'ein hagoral kove'ah mishana lachavertah. Here's the
problem. This year you drew the lots and this one, right, was
לעזאזל, la-Azazel. the other blood spilled, so we're not going to use
this, we're going to do a new pair. So the fact that
in 5774 this was לעזאזל, that doesn't help me for יום כיפור
Yom Kippur 5775. There, the identity has to be defined by the
lot I draw then, not by the lot I drew before. Okay,
so I don't know, so the גמרא Gemara says you can't use
it because last year's drawing of lots doesn't help for next year.
So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, ונייתי וניגריל, Veneisi venigril, so do
another drawing of lots this year, right? So you're telling me 5774
this was לעזאזל, so I can't use it, so that doesn't help
for 5775. Fine, use this and another goat and do it for
5775. You'll say, oh, it was too late, it was already designated
לעזאזל. No, you just got through telling me that last year doesn't
count for this year. So if last year's lot doesn't count for
this year, I can start afresh and do a new lot for
this year. Okay, so right, so לכתחילה lechatchila you're supposed to look
alike and be bought alike. Fine, that's לכתחילה, lechatchila, it's not בדיעבד,
bediavad, and now I have a goat here, use it for next
year, do a new drawing of lots and still use it for
next year. So the גמרא Gemara again gets back to גזירה, gezeira,
גזירה שמא יאמרו הגורל קובע משנה לחברתה. Gezeira shema yomru hagoral koveia
mishana lachaverta. No, we're afraid it doesn't look good. You drew lots
on it last year, and people see you using it this year,
people will think that last year's drawing of lots worked for the
following year. Right. Who's going to remember and how often is this
going to happen that people are going to think, and people will
see you drawing lots again this year, I don't know. Anyway, the
גמרא Gemara is not happy with the answer. גמרא Gemara says התינח
שעיר, Hatainach se'ir, fine, at most what they could explain is again
the goat case because there's this whole issue of drawing of lots.
פר מאי איכא למימר, Par mai ika lemeimar, you still can't explain
the ox case, the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. If he has the
ox from last year, use it again this year, there's no drawing
of lots. So of course we get our answer in our back
pocket. No, גזירה פר אטו שעיר. Gezeira par atu se'ir. No, we
don't want to use the ox because it will lead to the
goat case. The whole goat case was a גזירה gezeira about them
getting confused with the lot. So it's very it's getting very far-fetched,
right? The goat's so confused, does the lot work? The ox really
does work, it'll look like the case of the goat. So the
גמרא Gemara is not happy. You'll be happy to know the גמרא
Gemara isn't happy. ומשום גזירה ימותו? Umishum gezeira yamusu? Just because of
a גזירה gezeira they're all going to die? All of these are
גזירה: gezeira: the goat's a גזירה, gezeira,
the ox is a גזירה gezeira because of the goat,
and all of it's
going to die?
I mean you have a good question, just use it for next
year. אמרו רבנן קמי דאביי, Amru rabanan kamei de-Abaye, so the rabbis
said this over in front of אביי Abaye and they had the
following answer: גזירה משום חטאת שמתו בעליה. Gezeira mishum chatas she-mesu be'aleha.
The concern is another גזירה. gezeira. Why another גזירה gezeira works isn't
clear because we're not happy with גזירות, gezeiras, but maybe if you
make it a convincing גזירה gezeira we'll get it. So here is
their concern. They say here is the problem with the ox at
least. The goat maybe is the other reason we said about the
גורל, goral, but the ox, if you say use the ox for
next year, maybe next year we'll have a different כהן גדול, Kohen
Gadol, and as we knew in the Second Temple period that was
pretty common that next year you had a second כהן גדול, Kohen
Gadol, and therefore a new כהן גדול Kohen Gadol can't use the
other כהן גדול's Kohen Gadol's ox, right? That's a case where the
original owner died. So therefore we don't want you to hold over
till next year because it might be a different כהן גדול. Kohen
Gadol. Okay, with the פר. par. You don't have the ציבור tzibur
doesn't die, but that's the other concern about the lot for next
year. So wait a minute, the גמרא Gemara says התינח פר, Hatainach
par, fine, you've covered the ox. שעיר מאי איכא למימר? Se'ir mai
ika lemeimar? What's the issue with the goat? Because again we were
not so convinced that the concern of the lot is a convincing
reason not to use the goat for next year. So the גמרא
said גזירה שעיר אטו פר. Gezeira se'ir atu par. Okay, the other
way now! If we let you use the goat for next year
you'll come to use the ox for next year. So again this
is like גזירה לגזירה, gezeira le-gezeira, so the גמרא still isn't happy.
ומשום גזירה ימותו? Umishum gezeira yamusu? Again, it's, you know, maybe certain
גזירות gezeiras you could convince me, but this case that the ox
is a גזירה, gezeira, the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol will die and
the goat is a גזירה, gezeira, the ox, you're going to tell
me the goat's going to have to die? So wait a minute,
so the גמרא says now we're finally going to get to a
reason we can all understand: אלא גזירה משום חטאת שעברו שנתה. Ela
gezeira mishum chatas she-avru shenasa. No, it's a concern that it'll be
more than a year old and if the goat is more than
a year old you can't use it. So the גמרא says גזירה!
gezeira! What do you mean it might be more than a year
old? עיקרא דחטאת שעברה שנתה היא, Ikra de-chatas she-avrah shenasa hi, which
is what we should have started with! The goat is definitely more
than a year old! That's why you can't use the goat. The
ox we'll figure out, the ox maybe we gave a good reason
that the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol might die and he often would
die, so you can't use the ox next year because the original
owner is dead. You want a reason for the goat? I'll tell
you why you can't use the goat next year, it'll be more
than a year old and you can't use a goat that's more
than a year old. That's a pretty good reason. So now the
גמרא is going to explain why we had to say a גזירה
gezeira it will be more than a year old and not it
will definitely be more than a year old and we'll read this
one thing and with this we'll conclude. הא לא קשיא, Ha lo
kashya, there's a way That by next יום כיפור Yom Kippur, it
could still be considered a year old. How is that? כי דרבי,
Kiderabbi, like Rabbi, דתניא, Detanya, שנת תמימה, Shenat temima, when you sell
the house in a walled city, if it goes a full year
and you don't redeem it, it gets it gets permanently sold to
the guy who purchased it. So what's the definition of a full
year? מונה שלוש מאות שישים וחמישה יום כימות החמה דברי רבי. Moneh
shlosh meos shishim vechamisha yom kiyemos hachama divrei Rabbi. Rabbi says since
it says full year, you go by a solar year, not by
a lunar year. וחכמים אומרים, Vechachamim omrim, three hundred and sixty-five days?
But the sages say no, מונה שנים עשר חודש מיום ליום. Moneh
shenem asar chodesh miyom leyom. You do twelve lunar months. ואם נתעברה,
Ve'im nisabrah, if it was a leap year, נתעברה למוכר, Nisabrah lamocher,
then that then the leap year then the seller gets that extra
month to still redeem it. So now what the גמרא is assuming
is an amazing thing, that mostly we'd thought Rabbi said it because
for once the תורה Torah says full year. So full year tells
you solar year. But the גמרא is now suggesting that according to
Rabbi, whenever you have this idea of year, you would go by
a solar year. So if there's a הלכה halacha that the goat
has to be within a year old from birth, it's within a
solar year. So it's possible by next יום כיפור, Yom Kippur you
see, if this goat was exactly eight days old when יום כיפור
Yom Kippur came around, and it's a normal lunar year, by next
יום כיפור it will still be less than three hundred and sixty-five
days old. So it's theoretically possible that it will be within the
year. But still, the easier answer, forget גזירה. gezeirah. The easier explanation
of why we don't use the goat next year is because ninety-nine
times out of a hundred, even according to Rabbi and a hundred
times out of a hundred according to וחכמים, vachachamim, by next year
the goat is too old. That's why you can't hold over the
goat. Why you can't hold over the ox, right now the one
reason we have is because the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol might have
died and then the ox won't be usable. So we now have
a pretty good explanation both for the ox and for the goat.
We will continue with this discussion tomorrow.